"DHEA: What Is It and What Are Its Benefits?"
Dehydroepiandrosterone, DHEA,
is the most abundant
steroid hormone
circulating in the blood,
or rather, prohormone.
It's produced largely
by the adrenal glands
and is then
converted locally in tissues
into androgens,
male sex hormones,
or estrogens,
female sex hormones.
DHEA production in the body
peaks between the ages
of 25 to 35,
and then gradually
starts to decline
about 2 percent every year.
By one's 80s, DHEA production
is down about 80 percent
from peak values
in early adulthood.
Cross-sectional studies
found a link
between low DHEA levels
and impaired sexual function,
less vitality,
depressed mood,
lower bone mineral density,
and compromised
cognitive performance
in terms of executive function,
concentration, and memory.
Combined with
interventional studies
done on rodents
showing a wide range
of beneficial effects,
DHEA was heralded
as an "anti-aging
superhormone panacea,"
even though
rodent adrenal glands
don't even produce the stuff.
But U.S. DHEA sales grew
to more than $50 million a year
on the premise that
replenishing youthful levels
might have restorative effects.
Given the Premarin debacle
with estrogen replacement,
showing that the reversing
of age-related hormonal decline
can sometimes
do more harm than good,
clinical trials
were desperately needed.
But because DHEA
can't be patented,
there's been
little research interest
among drug companies
to study it.
In fact,
part of its mass appeal is that,
due to a legal loophole,
DHEA is the only steroid
that's not considered
a controlled substance,
and therefore is available
over the counter
as a "dietary supplement,"
rather than
a prescription only drug.
Thankfully,
a series of long-term,
high-quality randomized
controlled trials
started to be published
within the last 20 years,
and early enthusiasm
was replaced
by a sober skepticism
as the "panacea"
repeatedly failed
to beat the placebo.
The promised
DHEA fountain of youth
was drying up.
A review of about two dozen
randomized controlled trials
of oral DHEA
in postmenopausal women
failed to find evidence
of improvements
in sexual function,
psychological well-being,
or cognitive performance.
However, there may be a role
for intravaginal DHEA
for vaginal atrophy,
which I covered before.
A meta-analysis
of about two dozen
randomized controlled trials
of DHEA in elderly men
similarly found no evidence
of benefits for metabolism,
bone health, sexual function,
or quality of life,
nor does there seem to be
a cognitive benefit.
The only benefit found in men
was a relatively trivial drop
in body fat compared to placebo,
less than one pound over a span
of eight months.
But in women,
DHEA may benefit fertility.
Fertility in women
starts declining gradually
but significantly at age 32,
but then more rapidly
after age 37,
but DHEA may help.
Side-effects
of taking DHEA supplements
include acne,
oily skin and hair,
and an increase in body hair
and blood levels
of the cancer-promoting
growth hormone IGF-1.
As with any supplement,
there are concerns
about quality control issues.
Some so-called
"DHEA" supplements
just blatantly lie
and have no DHEA whatsoever,
or up to, like,
150 percent of the listed dose.
For these and other reasons,
DHEA supplements
are not recommended.
Are there natural ways
to boost DHEA,
for example,
for the fertility benefit?
Lower protein intake is
associated with higher levels,
and an interventional trial
found increasing fiber intake
actively raised levels,
so what about
putting them together?
Enter: "Short-Term Impact
of a Lactovegetarian Diet."
After just five days
on an egg-free vegetarian diet,
blood levels
of the DHEA precursor rose
nearly 20 percent.
Or you can do it the other way:
Take those already eating
a plant-based diet
and switch them
to a conventional diet,
and their DHEA drops
up to nearly 20 percent.
The bodies of those
eating plant-based
appear to hold onto
the hormone better,
less urinary excretion,
which is normally something
you only see in fasting.